<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<diseases>
<disease id="flu">
<image>https://cdn3.vectorstock.com/i/1000x1000/58/82/influenza-concept-in-circle-with-thin-line-icons-vector-20825882.jpg</image>
<overview>Influenza, which is also known as “flu”, is a disease which can spread very quickly upon human contact. According to World Health Rankings, Influenza along with Pneumonia, is ranked fifth in the top 50 death causes in Mauritius. H1N1 virus is one component of the seasonal flu vaccine. The flu shot also protects against two or three other influenza viruses that are expected to be the most common during the flu season. </overview>
<causes>A person can easily catch flu when he inhales the virus thrust in the air when an infected person sneezes or coughs. A person can also be contaminated with the flu when he physically get in contact with an infected person, for example; shaking hands.
</causes>
<symptoms> A person suffering from influenza will usually show these symptoms: &#13;&#10;
• High Fever &#13;&#10;
• Headache &#13;&#10;
• Aches and pains &#13;&#10;
• Extreme exhaustion &#13;&#10;
• Chest discomfort and cough &#13;&#10;
• Dizziness &#13;&#10;
• Sore throat
</symptoms>
<treatment>Influenza antiviral drugs can be used to treat influenza. Antiviral drugs can be in the form of pills, liquid, an inhaled powder, or an intravenous solution.  Check with your doctor promptly if you are at high risk of serious flu complications. According to health experts and government agencies around the world, the single best way to protect oneself from catching flu is to get vaccinated every year. \n
Herbal medicines for treating influenza: \n
• Eucalyptus: crushed leaves \n
• Pervenche a fleurs blanches:  Root and bark decoction used for leprosy, respiratory problems, influenza and an arborifacient. \n
• Fougkre polypode : Leaf decoction used for cough, influenza, dysentery and against skin rash. \n
• Bois sureau: Leaf decoction used for coughs and influenza \n
 
 Citation:  Ameenah G. Fakim (1990) Medicinal Plants of Mauritius, International Journal of Crude Drug Research, 28:4, 297-308, DOI: 10.3109/13880209009082837
</treatment>
<prevention>
 • Get vaccinated \n
• Eat and drink safely \n
• Keep away from animals \n
• Reduce your exposure to germs \n
• Avoid sharing body fluids \n
• Avoid non-sterile medical or cosmetic equipment \n
</prevention>
</disease>
<disease id="gastro">
<image>https://nurseslabs.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/FT-Gastroenteritis-Nursing-Care-Plans.png</image>
<overview>Gastroenteritis is usually the condition when a person’s stomach and intestines are said to be inflamed and irritated. In Mauritius, there are 35, 165 cases of gastroenteritis recorded in Hospitals and 70, 092 cases in community health centers as of 2016. (Health Statistics Unit, Ministry of Health and Quality of Life, 2017)
Food and water-borne illnesses can occur in any country. When we are travelling, we are more likely to be unfamiliar with our food – we won’t always know where it came from, how it was prepared, or who handled it. Some of us are also more inclined to take risks by trying local delicacies and eating from various food vendors. You can prevent gastrointestinal infections when you know the risks, make safe choices, and practice good hygiene. The golden rule is: Boil it, Cook it, Peel it, or Forget it!

</overview>
<causes>The infectious disease can be spread by:
Contact with someone who is infected with the virus.
Contaminated food or water.
Unwashed hands after going to the bathroom.

Exposure to contaminated food is a common source of gastrointestinal illnesses. Before we eat our food, it encounters growers, processors, storage facilities, retailers, and food handlers that can introduce pathogens such as e. coli, Clostridium botulinum, and salmonella. Contamination can also occur through:

Washing food with untreated water
Cross-contamination of raw and cooked items
Improper cooking, storage, and refrigeration
Unsanitary cooking tools and utensils
Poor hand hygiene</causes>
<symptoms>The symptoms of gastroenteritis are:
Diarrhea
Vomiting
Stomach pain
Cramps
Fever
Nausea
Headache
Dehydration
Loss of appetite
Poor feeding in infants

Depending on the cause, symptoms may appear within one to three days after infection and can range from mild to severe. Symptoms usually last one or two days, but occasionally may persist for up to ten days. 
</symptoms>
<treatment>Most people with gastroenteritis recover within several days without the need for medical treatment, as long as they stay properly hydrated. To help keep yourself comfortable and prevent dehydration while you recover, try the following:  

Stop eating solid foods to let your stomach settle
Avoid dairy products, caffeine, alcohol, nicotine
Avoid sugary, fatty or highly seasoned foods
Drink plenty of liquid every day, taking small, frequent sips, including clear thin broths or soups, diluted non-caffeinated sports drinks (e.g. Powerade or Gatorade), and rehydration formulas (e.g. Gastrolyte) that are available without prescription from a pharmacy
Ease back into eating slowly with bland easy-to-digest foods such as, crackers, toast, bananas, rice and potatoes
Make sure that you get plenty of rest
Avoid taking non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), such as aspirin, ibuprofen, and diclofenac, for pain relief as they can make your stomach more upset
Paracetamol (e.g. Panadol) can be taken for fever and abdominal pain but it should be used cautiously.
For infants with gastroenteritis, let the baby's stomach rest for 15 to 20 minutes after vomiting or a bout of diarrhoea, then offer small amounts of liquid. Let the baby nurse if being breast-fed. If you are bottle-feeding, offer a small amount of an oral rehydration solution or regular formula. 

Anti-diarrhoeal medications, such as Imodium, can be taken to slow the diarrhoea. In most cases, however, it is better for the body to clear itself of the virus or bacteria causing the gastroenteritis. 

Mauritian herbal medicines:
Citronnier Med: Fruit juice and leaf infusion used for cough, respiratory congestion, fever, cough, colds, liver and gastrointestinal discomforts, nausea and ulcers. 
Brede martin Med: Leaf and stems eaten as a vegetableboiled for hypertension and anaemia. B: Leaf‘s toxic alkaloid solanine is acid, bitter, a gastrointestinal irritant, smoothmuscle and cardiac stimulant
</treatment>
<prevention>Food and water-borne illnesses can occur in any country. When we are travelling, we are more likely to be unfamiliar with our food – we won’t always know where it came from, how it was prepared, or who handled it. Some of us are also more inclined to take risks by trying local delicacies and eating from various food vendors. You can prevent gastrointestinal infections when you know the risks, make safe choices, and practice good hygiene. The golden rule is: Boil it, Cook it, Peel it, or Forget it!
Always exercise caution with your drinking water. In areas where hygiene and sanitation are challenging to maintain, taking precautions with drinking water is essential.
If you are unsure about the tap water quality at your destination, bring the water to a rolling boil.
Always exercise caution when eating high risk foods. Reduce your risk of illness by practicing food safety and following good hand hygiene practices at your destination.
</prevention>
</disease>
<disease id="pinkeye">
<image>https://thumbs.dreamstime.com/z/woman-conjunctivitis-closeup-view-patient-pinkeye-infectious-viral-disease-medical-concept-anatomy-people-vector-106358021.jpg</image>
<overview>Conjunctivitis is another infectious disease which is commonly known as “Pink Eye”. It is the redness and inflammation of the clear membranes covering the whites of the eyes and the membranes on the inner part of the eyelids. (Anon n.d.) In Mauritius, the records show a statistic of 24, 823 cases in hospitals and 42, 332 cases in community health centers as of 2016. (Health Statistics Unit, Ministry of Health and Quality of Life, 2017)
</overview>
<causes>It is an extremely contagious disease. The causes are:
Sharing object with an infected person
Spread through coughing and sneezing
</causes>
<symptoms>A person infected with Pinkeye will show the following symptoms:
Eye redness
Itching of eye
Swelling of eye
Eye tearing
Burning sensation in the eye
Mild sensitivity to light 
</symptoms>
<treatment>Viral conjunctivitis will usually disappear on its own (within two to four weeks) without use of anti-viral medication. Symptoms may be relieved by the application of cold compresses and eye drop lubricants, such as artificial tears. However, because viral conjunctivitis is highly contagious for two weeks after symptoms first appear, as long as the eyes are red, it is important to take steps to prevent its spread to other people. 

In cases of bacterial conjunctivitis, frequent use of a clean, warm washcloth to remove the discharge may be required. Antibiotic eye-drops or ointment prescribed by a doctor will be needed to help clear up the infection. Oral antibiotics may be required for treatment of some infections. With treatment, bacterial conjunctivitis usually resolves within one to two weeks. </treatment>
<prevention>Infectious forms of conjunctivitis are highly contagious, being spread by direct contact with infected people for up to two weeks after their symptoms first appear (ie: as long as their eyes are red).  Maintaining good personal and household hygiene is the key to preventing the spread of infectious conjunctivitis:

Avoid contact with people who have conjunctivitis
Disinfect household surfaces, e.g. doorknobs and countertops
Keep your fingers away from your eyes
Avoid rubbing your eyes
Wash your pillow cases often
Wash your hands often, and using disposable paper towels for drying your hands
Ensure that eye drops and ointments, facecloths, towels, and pillow slips are not shared
Use and care for your contact lenses correctly

Additionally, children should not attend childcare centres or school when they have signs of conjunctivitis.</prevention>
</disease>
<disease id="utr">
<image>https://thumbs.dreamstime.com/z/upper-respiratory-tract-infections-uri-urti-symptoms-treatment-line-icons-set-vector-infographics-upper-respiratory-tract-107801687.jpg</image>
<overview>An upper respiratory function is an infectious process of any of the components of the upper airway. Examples of these infections include rhinitis (inflammation of the nasal cavity), sinus infection, common cold etc. This infection is the most common reason for doctor visits. In Mauritius as well, the records for patients is high with 253, 294 hospital cases and 440, 511 community health centre cases. (Health Statistics Unit, Ministry of Health and Quality of Life, 2017)</overview>
<causes>Upper respiratory infection can spread from one person to another by inhaling respiratory droplets from sneezing or coughing. The transmission can also occur by touching the nose or mouth by hand or other object exposed to the virus.</causes>
<symptoms>Symptoms of the infection include:
Cough
Sneezing
Nasal discharge
Nasal congestion
Runny nose
Fever
Scratchy/sore throat
Nasal breathing 
</symptoms>
<treatment>
Mauritian herbal medicines:
Eucalyptus Med: Crushed leaves used for respiratory problems, cough and influenza
Bigarade Med: Leaf infusion used for asthma, respiratory disorders, bronchitis, colds, coughs, fever, palpitations, insomnia and vomiting 
Citronnier Med: Fruit juice and leaf infusion used for cough, respiratory congestion, fever, cough, colds, liver and gastrointestinal discomforts, nausea and ulcers. 
Elaiti Med: Seed infusion used for peptic problems and respiratory disorders. 
</treatment>
<prevention>Frequent hand-washing is important to prevent spreading or contracting the infection. Avoiding close contact with people who have a respiratory infection. 
</prevention>
</disease>
</diseases>